"Is Soil Degradation Reducing
the Nutrition of Fruits and Vegetables?"
Internet articles
and the popular press
frequently state that
the mineral nutrient
composition of crops
has been declining
over the last 50 years
with titles like
"The great nutrient collapse,"
blamed in part on the purported
nutrient depletion of the soil.
This narrative is touted
by the leading
dietary supplement
trade association,
but is it true?
This is probably
the most cited study,
comparing the nutrient content
of U.S. fruits and vegetables
between 1950 and 1999,
and about half,
seven of the 13
nutrients tested,
showed no significant decline,
and the six that did
only declined by about
15 percent on average.
A similar study in the UK
looking at mineral content
had similar findings
with declines in about half.
Of course, the drop in sodium
doesn't matter;
we get too much of it as it is,
and most people
get more than enough copper.
But the ten percent drop
in magnesium is significant,
and though the drop in iron
looks precipitous,
the absolute drop is tiny,
since fruits and veggies
have so little to begin with.
Australian researchers
had similar findings:
a halving of iron in fruit
over the last few decades,
but the absolute drop
is like 0.2 mg per serving,
which is about 1/50th
of the recommended
daily allowance for most people,
and the same with zinc.
And there was actually
an increase in grains.
As you can see, there was just
a few milligrams difference
in calcium or magnesium,
where the RDA is in
the hundreds of milligrams.
So, with such small
absolute differences,
any true decrease
in mineral content
is unlikely
to have a large impact
on nutritional intake.
And it's not clear
if these changes are even real.
These comparisons of historical
food composition tables
are not a reliable way
to determine changes
in nutrient composition
of foods over time,
since they are just
unmatched snapshots in time
not meant to sync up.
So, these may have been
different varieties,
or there may have been
differences
in ripeness, season, location.
If you look at
the levels of minerals
in the soil itself,
you don't tend
to see declining levels,
and in some cases,
you actually see
a significant rise
in mineral levels
nearly across the board
over the last half century.
So, where is this gloomy
supplement industry propaganda
coming from?
There's been a concern
that rising CO2 levels
might reduce nutrients in crops,
but the largest recorded change
was a 59 percent increase
in total antioxidant content,
thanks to higher
phytonutrient levels.
What about the concern
that modern varieties
grow so much larger and faster,
potentially creating a trade-off
between yield
and nutrient concentration?
One way to study this
is to grow a whole bunch
of different varieties
released over the years
under the same conditions,
which is what these researchers
did with broccoli.
14 cultivars
released over 50 years,
and they found that there was
no clear change over time
in mineral content,
though they did find
that larger heads of broccoli
did tend to have
lower mineral content;
something to keep in mind
next time you shop.
As for the dietary supplement
trade association's claim
that Americans don't get the
nutrients they need from foods?
Well, for example,
only half of Americans
reach even 75 mg
of vitamin C a day--
less than the amount
in a single orange.
So, why aren't Americans
getting enough fruit
and vegetable nutrients?
Because they aren't eating
enough fruits and vegetables.
They don't need pills,
they just need produce.
So, even if there really is
15 percent less vitamin C
in today's broccoli,
that just may mean
you have to eat
six florets of today's broccoli
instead of five florets
from yesteryear.